A few months ago, I discussed a clinical
trial where people with advanced stages
of cancer, all kinds, were put on a
serine and glycine-free diet, and many
of them were able to see mass reversal
of their cancer. Now, I use this one
example as a staggering illustration.
The tumor is on the left, and then 9
weeks later, the tumor is gone on the
right. However, with a bit of reasoning,
you probably came to the same conclusion
that many did. Hold on. If we remove
glycine and serine, then we see cancer
improvements. So, does that mean that
glycine and serine worsen cancer? Should
I stop supplementing with these amino
acids? That's when I turned to six more
studies, which ultimately taught me a
mind-blowing relationship between these
amino acids, one in particular, and
cancer. But, one study specifically
completely flipped the script. So,
should we be worried? Is supplementation
a bad idea? This idea that serine and
glycine are involved in cancer
progression is not a new one. It's been
studied well before this small clinical
trial that I mentioned in passing. In
the simplest explanation, the amino acid
serine can be converted in your cells to
glycine. Both glycine and serine are
made of carbon atoms, and these carbon
atoms can be donated to other molecules
vital for the cell survival and growth.
For example, DNA synthesis, for the
copying of cancer cells genes to create
a new cancer cell. So, both glycine and
serine can donate carbons to DNA
synthesis. This whole process is called
one-carbon metabolism. That's really all
you need to know for your mind to get
blown later. This clinical trial isn't
the only one looking at restriction of
both of these amino acids and improving
cancer outcomes, though other research
is in animals. The advantage of this
research is that it can also be directly
looking at survival, which we can't do
in a clinical human research. For
example, here, we're looking at survival
by purely putting animals on a serine
and glycine-restricted diet in two
different types of cancer. So,
intestinal cancer and lymphoma. The
higher the lines, the better the
survival over time on the horizontal
axis. The blue line is the serine and
glycine-restricted condition, and
clearly there's better cancer outcomes,
confirming the results in humans in a
different way. Though, the human data
also included conventional anti-cancer
therapies like immunotherapy. The point
here being that in early human research
and preclinical research across multiple
cancers, restricting glycine and serine
leads to better cancer outcomes, to put
it mildly. Okay, interesting, right?
But, that's just confirming what we
already knew if you saw the previous
analysis. The thing is, though, that
we're manipulating two variables in
tandem, glycine and serine.
Are they both problematic or just one?
Now, here's where the plot thickens.
Here, we're looking at cancer growth
over time. Now, this is a simple
experiment, a control condition where
all the amino acids are fed to the
cancer, shown in blue, the complete
condition, and then the dual restriction
of glycine and serine or each restricted
individually. Now, you don't need to
know what P53 and the different
deletions, it won't matter anyway. All
you need to know is that if the lines go
up, there's more cancer cells. Now, the
purple line is what we'd expect. The
dual restriction restricts cancer's
ability to multiply. But, to tease out
which of these two has the greatest
impact, we should focus on the red and
the green line. Now, you might already
see it. That red line is perfectly
consistent with the total amino acid
pool present, the control. In simplified
terms, glycine restriction does not
restrict cancer growth, but serine
restriction does. Now, there's more to
it than that, considering that we're
looking at cells in a dish, but this is
extremely important information, as
you'll see. In fact, this was further
confirmed in a detailed study focusing
on the very question, is it glycine or
serine that's the issue? They too
confirm it's serine, not glycine. Now,
let me transport you back to what I
mentioned that you should remember, the
one-carbon metabolism. Remember that? If
not, don't sweat it. I'll remind you.
Remember, the pool of serine molecules
in your cells, including cancer cells,
is converted to glycine molecules. Both
of these amino acids, glycine and
serine, contribute carbons to the
production of new DNA, technically
nucleic acids, which are the building
blocks for DNA, genes. Now, one
experiment that we, scientists, can do
is tag molecules like amino acids so
that we can track where they end up in
the body or even within cells. So, what
happens when cancer cells are exposed to
tagged glycine? Something remarkable.
Here, there's three different
concentrations of glycine being added to
the cells, and because they're tagged,
we can see where they go. Here, we're
measuring serine production. So, as
glycine is increased, serine is
increased within the cells. But, wait.
Didn't we say that serine is converted
to glycine?
And why does any of this matter?
Well, yes, glycine is created from
serine, except the reaction is what's
called in biochemistry as reversible. As
in, if there's a lot of glycine, no more
is converted from serine, but instead,
glycine begins being converted to
serine. That's part one.
The second part, the consequential part,
is shown here. I know this looks
confusing, but we can ignore most of it.
To orient you, here's serine, here's
glycine, and here are the end product,
the nucleic acids for DNA production and
more. Now, notice how there's a carbon
taken from serine in the conversion to
glycine, and notice how it eventually
leads to more carbons being donated in
this pathway for the production of these
nucleic acids. That's what I explained
to you earlier, one-carbon metabolism,
in fewer words and less diagrams. Now,
what do you think happens when we have a
scenario like what I just showed you?
Glycine is increased to a point that
serine is produced, the reversible
reaction. This all-important carbon that
gets taken off serine is now going to go
in the opposite direction. So, what do
you think happens to this pathway? It
falls apart. Consequently, that means
that cancer cell can't produce nucleic
acids as easily, and it also can't
multiply or repair its genome as
readily, which makes it especially
vulnerable to damage. How freaking cool
is that? Glycine is a double agent.
The main point, so we don't get lost in
the weeds, is that the amino acid of
greater concern in cancer is serine,
based on the data available, and
depriving glycine may have no real
impact. But, that last statement isn't
entirely accurate, right? We just saw
how overwhelming cells with glycine
reverses this one-carbon metabolism. So,
do we have any evidence that
supplementing glycine may actually
help against cancer? I'm going to get
into that now, but if you're interested
in a deeper dive on one-carbon
metabolism, more on glycine's role in
cancer, and even additional ways that
cancer cells are stressed by these amino
acids, check out my full video. It comes
with an article, as all my full analyses
do, and a lot of other stuff.
Like this stuff right here. So, if
you're interested, join the PhysioTic
Insiders. It's my premium research
platform, and it includes all of my work
in multiple formats and more. The link
to join the PhysioTic Insiders is in the
description box. I hope to see you
there. So, clearly realizing that
glycine may be a double agent, and the
mechanisms by which it does that is
mind-blowing. But, do we actually have
any evidence of the opposite of what
we've been looking at so far? As in,
when we supplement glycine, raising
glycine levels, do we see improvements
in cancer? The answer is, well,
look for yourself. If we look at
preclinical models again, but this time
it's a group fed glycine or a group fed
normal food without especially high
glycine amounts, I'll just say that the
higher the lines go, the more the
cancer's tumor grows. It's pretty
obvious that glycine supplementation
dramatically slows cancer progression,
and in fact, similar results are shown
here, too. So, across a few preclinical
studies, additional glycine inhibits
cancer growth. And while unconfirmed, it
could be due to this reversal of this
one-carbon metabolism. Now, this is a
pretty complex topic, and I don't I
don't want to leave the wrong impression
because we're mixing and matching data
across different types of studies,
different cancers, and different
experiments. So, the translation to
day-to-day life is difficult. I'm
currently thinking about it this way.
These data, as incomplete as they are,
indicate that if you're supplementing
with glycine or even consuming sizable
amounts of serine, and you don't have
cancer, there's zero reason to stop,
especially since the data is panning out
more favorably, especially for glycine,
even beyond cancer studies. Now, on the
other hand, the data is entirely too
incomplete to make any strong statements
in relation to cancer. It seems unlikely
that glycine contributes, but that's
based on cell studies paired to animal
studies and across few different cancer
types. It isn't strong evidence to
change behavior. It's true that we have
this one clinical trial where both amino
acids are restricted, but this is also a
phase one trial. So, we need much more
clarity even in the human research. So,
the risk benefit is going to be up to
the individual, but just know that what
evidence we have up to now is incomplete
for any clinician or ethical researcher
to offer any strong recommendations. So,
the conservative approach would be to
ignore these data until more data
emerges and the more aggressive approach
would be to follow the results of the
clinical trial, not the preclinical data
that we've been covering here. In fact,
if you're looking for more details on
the clinical trial, I cover it in more
depth right here. I hope you found this
as weirdly fascinating as I did. I'll
catch you in the next one. Bye.